start recording. So let's start this out to start. Can you tell me a bit about your studies
and where modeling fits in, for example, in your program year and which courses involved modeling? P1)
(3
So I used modeling, let's say officially in the software engineering course and then use it
more unofficially, for example, in my job and in my dissertation, when I need to, you know,
demonstrate what a system does, I do some modeling not necessarily using any particular framework
or tool, but, you know, P2) (okay, okay. And in those both cases, what were the purpose of using modeling
in the context of the course? Like, for example, modeling requirements, designing the system,
modeling the business process of the system. And for example, for your work, I assume you just
actually modeling the system. Can you describe like that? P1)(Yeah, so for the course, I did it because,
you know, I had to and we were using it for like a video game. So we had to model some of the processes
in some of the, let's say, actions that like some of the characters of the game could take.
For my dissertation, I'm modeling a data mining tool. So the point of the modeling is to show
to the people reading it and that don't know about it, how it works in an easy way, you know,
in a visual way. And in the context of my work, I use it to model the system that we are building
because it has ground to be quite a big and complex system. So not only for us, but also for the
people that we are working with that aren't, you know, actually working on it. They are just,
so they understand like what we are doing, what's, you know, the design, why we do certain things
and stuff like that. P2) (Okay, okay, perfect. And you said one of those uses for like modeling,
you don't really have a specific framework, but for example, for the course, do you remember which
frameworks you used? For example, you are male, BPM and IR, I start. P1) (I think UML was the main
one we used. I don't remember if you used any other framework, but yeah, I remember UML quite
clearly. P2) (Okay, just for clarification, when, how long ago was that course? P1) (Two years ago.
Two years ago. P2)( Okay, okay, perfect. Now, I want to understand what modeling means to you and what
experience stand out like regarding modeling. So when you hear software modeling or conceptual
modeling, what comes to your mind like what is the thing that flashes in your mind like instantly,
maybe diagrams, documentation, abstraction. P1) (Absolutely. If I had to use a word abstraction.
Yeah. P2) (Okay, okay. So if you had to explain modeling to a colleague in one or two sentences,
what would you say? P1) (It's a way to abstract complex systems and processes, you know, visually.
So that people who maybe don't understand a lot of it can get a good grasp of it just by
looking at a diagram, for example. P2) (Okay, perfect, perfect. Do you see modeling as a useful like tool,
work or like just extra documentation, a communication tool or something else like do you see any useful
as in it? P1) (Yes, no doubt. I think modeling is very useful even when you are working alone because
sometimes certain concepts may be really complex and you can't really fit them in your mind. So,
you know, making a little diagram of things can, you know, simplify it not only for you, but,
you know, also for others who might want to see your work and how it works. P2) (Great perspective.
Can you remember a moment when modeling felt particularly useful maybe in your work or like your
dissertation thesis? P1) (In my dissertation for sure, because basically while I was working on my data
mining tool, I started with one approach and then I ended up switching that approach to another
approach. And in order to explain that to the people reading my dissertation, making a diagram
of how the old version worked and how the new version worked felt particularly useful since I could,
you know, visually demonstrate why one approach was so much simpler than the other, something that
maybe through words I wouldn't be able to explain as easily. P2) (Okay, okay. So, you believed that
modeling changed your understanding of the system and the problem like
it helped you understand better the system and communicate also communicate better the system
for someone. P1) (Yes, yes, yes, for sure, for sure. P2) (Okay, okay. Did modeling it affect
like your motivation and confidence like regarding the system and modeling itself? P1)
(Modeling made me feel like it was simpler. I feel like I understood it before and after,
but, you know, like, but looking at it made me feel, you know, like it was simpler in, I guess,
in a way made me slightly more confident, but I don't think it had like a huge difference.
It doesn't have a, I do feel like it has a huge difference on the people reading it though.
Okay. I feel more confident in being able to correctly betray my system. P2) (You don't think it
like motivated you to like work further into your system. Like, oh, now I have this model,
to model, I understand it better, I'm good to like start working better on the system.
You don't think that? P1) (Oh really, I think it was, you know, a means to an end, it was a good tool,
but it didn't, you know, change fundamentally how I work, I don't think. P2) (Okay, okay, perfect.
And can you remember a moment when modeling felt like confusing, pointless or frustrating? P1)
(Definitely in my course, in my software engineering course, because I had to use
certain frameworks, which I was not familiar with. So, you know, I had to learn them before I
actually started drawing. I didn't feel that as much in my work or in my dissertation,
because I didn't use any particular framework. I just drew something that I felt was intuitive,
and I feel like it was, you know, good enough. P2) (So, you think, what do you think made it frustrating
like that? From what I heard, I would say the notation, in this case, the frameworks you used,
and the tool, maybe the way the tool you used in the moment, do you perhaps remember which tool you
used? P1) (I don't say the tool itself was a problem. I remember when I used the tool, which I think
was draw you at the time, but I'm not 100% sure. I remember that it had a lot of features that
made it really easy to do. What I felt like was a little bit frustrating was trying to fit an
abstraction into an already made system, you know, because the system had already certain rules
that you had to follow, you know, the abstraction had to fit those rules, not something that, you know,
when I create myself, I feel like would be easier. P2) (What's your opinion, for example, in
about test ambiguity, which was the case of Frecolytes on feedback, like professor feedback,
group work, time pressure, like those aspects, do you have any opinion on those? Did they affect
your frustration, like negative feelings towards modeling? P1) (It made this feel like a chore.
Did I felt like, I don't know, it was like a short, a short just like any other, you know,
task I had to do in that project, so I don't think it was more frustrating than anything else,
you know, just another thing to do, you know. P2) (And what did you do next, like after that frustrating
moment, like you started, like, for example, copying patterns, just like regular patterns, like
doing the work automatically, US someone for all avoided modeling overall, or like, just when
we trial an error.) (And if it was like fitting, I think I was more like trial and error, you know,
I just tried to do something, you know, eventually I finished it, after finishing, I showed it to
the professor, a professor, does this look, you know, all right? He's like, yeah, that's about right,
and that's about it. P2) (Okay, perfect, perfect. If you could replay that situation, what do you think
would have helped you most? Like going back in time, it'd do software engineering course, like
that frustrating moment, what do you think would have helped you there to like overcome it? P1)
(I don't feel that way at all.
I don't think I can't really put my finger on anything specific because I feel like, you know,
it had the same difficulty you have when learning anything else, you know, it's just something
that new you have to learn in. P2) (But I can like, probe you with this, but for example, the
ceased like the problem dimension, like the size of the project you had to work, for example.
I remember, free call being a huge open source game with thousands and thousands.
P1)
(Yeah, yeah, what ended up happening, and it's just what I think made it, you know, not that hard,
was that we could choose what we wanted to model. So because I was a beginner at it, what I choose
was something that I felt like I could, you know, easily model, given those rules.
But if I had to model something, you know, that something told me, oh, you have to model this,
specifically, maybe then I would have had a bigger challenge ahead of me. P2)
(Okay, thanks, thanks. Now, I want to zoom in how you learn modeling, and what tends to be hard,
is it like different stages of doing. So when you learn a new modeling notation or framework,
I'm saying this new, but like, we can reference the best experience in this case, you know,
what was usually the hardest part at the beginning when learning it, like any specific, like,
knowing where to start, or P1)
(the thing that the hardest part about modding overall is how to represent relationships between
the objects. I feel like there's always a very big, you know, nuance there that you may not be
able to completely explain through an arrow, for example, or through a line, you know, just,
you know, for example, something that might not be easily differentiable through line pipes,
for example, you know. P2) (Okay, and what do you do to make sense out of it, like, search small
examples online, ask other people, watch tutorials with documentation. P1) (I think what I did at the time,
I think what I did at the time, and I think is what I applied was I looked at a model that was
already done, and I looked at what it was describing, and I looked at each relation, and I'm looking
at it like, okay, so this person is connected to this object, and this relation means that.
So if this means this, then in my project, this person to be related to that, I need to use, you
know, that arrow, for example, and if that's clear. I think I would like to see something that was
already done. Yeah, similar, similar problem, and you would just try to like, to do the same way
for your case. Replicate it. Exactly. P2) (So imagine you get a text description of the system, which is
like a common exam question, they just give you like, here, this system, and they ask you to
build a model for that system. What steps do you usually like personally take? Like, do you have
a plan in your mind like, okay, I should start with this and finish with this, or you just wing it? P1)
(I wouldn't say I have a plan, and I wouldn't say I wing it exactly, you know, I think I have a
way of thinking, and that's what I would apply to it. In this case, what I would try to do first,
probably, was I would probably start with drawing the like the object, you know, like, let's say,
a person or like a specific process. Yeah, exactly, exactly. And then after having that,
I would try to model the relationships between them. Okay. I usually feel like this makes it
more intuitive for me. You would start by placing the actors, the classes, probably the classes for it,
which is the most common. Because that feels more simple, you know, usually, like you say,
I say, you have a person, you have a class, you know, that's easier to model, I feel like,
in the relationship. P2) (So in your opinion, do you have a more like a structured strategy or like
more trial and error strategy approach to it? P1) (I would say more of a structure simply because I don't
think I have that much of a trial and error. Of course, there's a little bit. I would say everyone
probably does. But I would think that once I think about something in a certain way in terms of,
you know, modeling systems, I find it hard to buy myself, look at it another way, you know.
Okay. Okay. So after reading, let's say that it's an exam question, after reading it for the
first time, and I think this is a class, this is a person, this is whatever I would hardly find,
you know, through trial and error, that to be something else.P2) (Okay. Okay. And do you have any idea,
like, about how do you decide where is something that you should include or you shouldn't, like,
ignore on the diagram, like when modeling overall? Why decide what to ignore? Yeah. Like, for example,
relationships, if you think that relationship is pointless to put on the diagram, do you feel like
that sometimes, like, oh, yeah, I don't need to model this. P1) (I feel like I don't have enough
experience where that has happened enough times for me to have an opinion on it. Is that okay,
answer? P2)( Yeah, yeah, it's okay. Don't worry about it.P1) (I feel like from my experience, the systems
have been fairly simple and the relations that are there, you know, I can model them. So, yeah. P2)
(So just when you probably want to remember this, but like, if you ever been taught, like,
an explicit step-by-step approach to modeling, or did they just give you here the concepts,
here is like usually the final product, they need to model this and this, they did they like tell
you, okay, you should start by placing the actors, the, the, this and do this. Do you have any recall
of that or if you don't, it's okay. P1) (What I recall from the course I took was that in
the theoretical classes, I was taught, like, not necessarily a step-by-step, but, you know,
what each thing, you know, each image represents. Yeah. And then in the practical class, you know,
the professor, you know, modeled, like, resolved an exercise, let's say, of modeling,
but didn't necessarily say you should start with this, you should start with that. He did it
in his way and maybe I just copied it, you know. P2) (Okay. So it was never explicit. It was just like,
yeah, you had an example, the, the way that the professor resolved it, but they didn't totally,
like, ah, this is the first thing you should do, this is the second area, right? P1) (Yeah, I don't
remember being explicit. P2) (Okay, once you have a model, you finished modeling, exam question,
how do you decide whatever, like, the model is good enough or it doesn't need changes, like,
what is your criteria for that? If you have any. I can give you examples, like completeness,
if the model is complete, the model is consistent, readable, correct, matches the requirements of
the exercise, just simplicity. P1) (Okay, okay. I think I have two main ones, which is completeness and
simplicity, you know, if I can look at the model, have every relationship and, you know, every actor
in it, and apparently simply can understand, you know, what's going on. I think that's a good model. P2)
(Okay, okay, perfect. The answer. And did, I mean, the only course you had, did software,
like, engineering, give you, like, any quality rules, quality check list, like, to know,
evaluate the model? Probably did, but I assume you shouldn't remember by now. P1)
(It was probably thought, but I do not, you know, I did not memorize it. Yeah, okay,
it's, it's fair, it's normal. P2) (And do you compare your model with others? Like, check someone else's
model? Oh, yeah, I did this, but I didn't do this. If yes, the course, the course are like,
in general, in right now, for example, if you've seen some other person diagram for the thesis,
like, do you like, oh, yeah, it's similar, but it's missing this. Like, what do you look for if you
do this? If you don't, we can skip this. P1) (Yeah, I did, in my dissertation, for example,
I had some, my professor gave me some, you know, previous dissertations. I worked somewhat
similar to mine and I compared mine to theirs. And, you know, if I feel like mine is as simple
and, you know, understandable as theirs, I would consider it a good model. P2) So you were looking
for simplicity, basically, to see if like, those represent the system clearly P1), (yes, they're
very simple and clear and like, clarity of, you know, they were not searching, but, yeah,
clarity, yeah, I think it's clarity. Yeah, I think so, yes, because usually when I have to model
something, I have a very specific goal in mind, you know, I want to, when I'm modeling something,
I want to convey a message, you know, and if I feel like that, let's say, diagram is
conveying the correct message, then I consider it a good diagram. P2) (Okay, okay, perfect. Great.
Next I want to ask about tools and core setup, like because sometimes the experience depends a lot
on the environment, not just the notion notation. So if the class is the practical classes require you
to be on these old labs, computers, using old software, it might affect your like view of the
modeling experience. So I will ask you some questions related to that. What tools have you used
for modeling? You said you used draw a yo, probably paper, anything else? P1)(Yeah, paper for sure,
paper for sure. Mostly in my course, then I used draw you for my, for my dissertation, because
I had to draw like pipelines of like data mining, like I was saying, for my job, I actually used
canva, which might be, you know, somewhat an orthodox, but it was more of modeling how different,
like, you know, modules relate to each other. So it was more like, you know, text-based.
Yeah, that's why we used that. Yeah, I feel like that. P2) (How was it being like, what are your opinions?
Like, what do you like, what do you dislike? Like, for example, paper, maybe drawing is not your
favorite way of doing stuff. P1) (It's not. You know, I wouldn't think of paper, you know, in the
first place, because I think that the online tools are already so good and simple and intuitive and
fast that I feel like paper is almost a waste of time, you know. As long as, you know, the tools,
I can connect, you know, something in the middle of something to the something in the middle of
something else, you know. For example, provide templates, clarity, guidance, they can actually give
you say, like, oh, there's an error. This error is not fully connected stuff like that. P2) (Do you think
that influence your, like, your view of modeling, impact like how you view modeling, like, a proper tool? P1)
(I'm going to say no, despite everything you said, because I feel like nothing has really changed
my view of modeling that I had since I remember, because to me, you know, modeling is a means to an
end. And I don't think anything has really changed that. I don't think anything is particularly hard. P2)
(Let me reward this. Do you think that tools make modeling feel harder or easier than it should be? P1)
(I think tools make modeling. That's an interesting question. I'm going to say that modeling
as an inherent difficulty, which the tools can't really simplify, you know. I think they have
I think the tools have simplified as much as they can in the sense that they make, you know,
drawing the things, you know, actual, the actual drawing make it easy. But the hard part for me
is thinking what I should put where, you know. So if we had, like, an idea for modeling, if
that was even possible, maybe that would help. But I cannot imagine that being, you know, made. So
now the tools, you know, I understand where they're going. It's more like the difficulty is more
mental than like too related. It's not difficult to draw it or like to think, but it's more about
what I should put where that you're saying, like exactly what what abstractions to use, what to
represent. P2) (Yeah. But don't you think that this is not something that you think that if a tool
actually addressed those, like for example, the tool would suggest you to, okay, this connection
would be good. You should probably do this or like should check stuff like, oh, this relationship
is not right. Don't you think it would facilitate? P1) (Yeah, for sure. For example, other type of modeling,
which I'm not sure is what you are considering. For example, in databases, you know, those types
of models. Yeah, yeah, it's modeling. For example, data type of modeling, I think that would be
really useful. You know, when you are modeling a big database, which I had to do recently as well in
what was it called? Of course, it was database systems. Yeah. We had to like look at models and
we didn't actually have to do, but actually we did have to do some, but on paper. So it wasn't
really using the tools. But if I had to do, you know, because I remember that from the original
databases, which we did have to do on a program, if we have an IDE that will tell us like, for
example, wait, this relationship with this doesn't make sense because, you know, it's a circle or
I don't know how to better explain it. Yes, they will be very useful. P2) (Like the tool, if the tool could
guide you through the development, the modeling process, it would be a positive thing, right? P1) (Like,
it would improve. Yes, I would think so. Especially for bigger models. I, something I did not work
with a lot was like really big models. So some of those questions, I feel like would be better
answer if I had, but yeah, I can imagine how big models would really make use of those kinds of
features. P2) (You assume that tools can be helpful for like modeling, for like understanding how
modeling, even with like the, the notations always that stuff works, right? P1) (Yeah, yeah, yeah. P2)
(Probably move on because getting, getting tight on time. So thinking about modeling assignments
projects, with kind of domains or examples that you work with, you said you worked on the software
engineering, which was the free call if I recall correctly the game. Yeah. You probably also did
some other like domains for your personal work and the TZ. So where any domains, especially
interesting or meaningful to you? P1) (I would say for sure explaining a data mining pipeline, you know,
in my case, what happened was that I had to aggregate data from multiple different APIs,
from multiple different sources with multiple different fields. And through words, you know,
just explaining it through text would be really hard to do. So adding a diagram to do that,
you know, I feel like really helps. P2) (Okay. Regarding the domains where I'm talking about the
main is more like the field. Like, for example, the free call was a game. Did you find it like
boring, alienating? Like, for example, gaming is not for everyone. Do you think that like picking up
a good subject, good domain is important for like motivation regarding like learning, modeling,
software engineering overall? P1) (I guess definitely because I think, you know, surely everyone has
preferences. So, you know, choosing something that that person prefers would be ideal. But I don't
think there is, P2) (you know, like, for example, if you were allowed to choose your own domain,
did you do you think your own like topic to model to do? Did you do you think that would change
the motivation effort like regarding the modeling? In your case P1), (yes, without a doubt. And I think
it would make it easier, you know, to specially starting out if you can, you know, choose something
that's more familiar to you. Yeah. P2) (Okay. Perfect. Okay. Then, how did feedback on modeling work in
your courses? Like, do you remember if the teacher just gave you grades, only comments,
toolbikes, checks, peer review, like, you know, when I ask the, yeah P1), (I guess that's somewhat sure,
you know, the teachers, you know, I would, if I had a doubt, I could show it to them and they would,
you know, yeah, this is good, this is bad, this is probably it's not something that you want to do.
But, you know, I think if I didn't have the, you know, the initiative, it was pretty much just
a grade, you know, we went to the discussion, the teacher had reviewed the work supposedly before
we went there. And when we got there, we had the discussion. The models were not that much of a
subject. P2) (Okay. So, you think that at the end, the grade was given. Do you think that the teachers
didn't put the effort to actually go and give feedback if you were not the one taking a day initiative,
if you were not the one going to the pitch and I see like, look, is this model looking good for you?
You wouldn't go, you wouldn't go out of this way to do that. P1)
(I would say so because I think that modeling didn't feel like the main, you know, worry of the
professors. Okay. So, it was like something, you know, something else that you had to do, you know,
there were some other things that we had to do, like code smells and stuff like that, you know.
So, everything felt like a small part and you know, model was one of those small parts.
One of those small parts. P2)(Okay. And about the reviews, like the feedback,
was it early enough to help you improve on the modeling or was it only at the end? P1)
(I remember like the end of the course, we had that discussion with the teachers,
they were they like, gave feedback.P2) (Do you think if they gave feedback earlier on, it would
or like multiple times like the iterative process, would it like upgrade like the model? P1)
(I would think so, yeah, because I remember that, you know, I think there was,
I'm not sure if we had to submit things by stages, I think there was like two stages maybe.
But I feel like, for example, if they made more stages, we're like one, for example,
first stage code smells, second stage modeling, you know, at each stage they gave feedback,
I feel like that would have been really helpful, you know, for improving our models.
But I understand if the teachers, you know, don't have time for all that. P2)
(Okay. Okay. Perfect. Now, Leslie and this topic, did work group work help or heard modeling,
like learning modeling? Group work, like I said, was a group project. What were your opinion on the
group project, the way it was structured? P1) (My opinion is that it helped as much as having someone
else doing the same thing as you helps, you know. But since each person had to make their own model,
it wasn't that much of a group project, I felt like. P2) (Okay. Okay. Perfect. Now,
last couple of questions, it's about like, I want to understand what good modeling skill means to
you and what you'd improve. So if you think of modeling as a skill, what should a good
modeler be able to do in your opinion? P1) (Going back to like, you know, that same point I made
earlier, making something simple and, you know, give it like a lot of clarity, you know,
something that you can look at and, you know, intuitively understand.
Abstraction. It's the main one. P2) (Okay. Do you think it's soft skills matter or is it mostly
technical? By soft skills, I mean, like communication, negotiation, teamwork, stuff like that. P1)
(For modeling, specifically. For making the model itself, I would say now, for presenting it to
other people and explaining it, yes P2). (Okay. Okay. Don't you think that, for example, having good
communication skill would like help you to develop a model in a more presentable way. Like,
hmm, I want to communicate this P1). (No, probably, yes, but I agree to which it would help.
I think it's very little P2). (Okay. Okay. So it's mostly technical for you in your opinion. P1)
(Modeling itself. Yes, I would say so. P2) (Okay. Okay. Yeah. So if you could change one or two things
in how modeling is starting your degree, what would you change? Like explanations, materials,
but I don't know if the PowerPoints like were greater or not, the tools, different tool setup,
better training, assignments, domains, like be able to choose your own domain instead of having
the free code, having better feedback. P1) (Right. Yeah. I mean, starting out choosing your own domain
would definitely be good. But at the same time, I think, you know, a foreign domain is also good
because, you know, in real life, you're not always going to have to model something that's familiar
to you. So, you know, having having to model something that you are not familiar with is definitely
useful. But in terms of helping, I would say maybe, I guess just giving more of an emphasis on it,
I feel like it is, you know, something that's not very impassaged, you know, or the passage.
I'm sorry. But I think you understand what I mean P2). (Yeah. So that's your opinion that would you
change? P1) (Yes, I would just give it a little more emphasis, you know, if people find it to be that
important. Okay. And also make it something, you know, maybe slightly more specific. I don't know
if that helps a lot, but I feel like when we had to model it was just like, you know, one of the other
tasks that we had to do on that project, it didn't feel like, you didn't feel like it had a lot of
purpose, you know, the specific task that we did. Sure, it helped, but it was not like that helpful.
I feel like giving a very specific purpose, you know, you want to show this to when you are
modeling something. I feel like that would help. Yeah. Giving like a more concrete thing, like,
you need to present the system in a clear way to a certain stakeholder that has this
knowledge. For example, let me give you an example, you know, instead of doing something like,
okay, model this system to the stakeholder, I would say, model this system to show this to the
stakeholder. You know what I'm saying? P2) (Yeah, specific concrete, like, specific message features,
like specific part of the system. I see, I see. So yeah, not just generic yet. Yeah, yeah.
One final question. It's an open question. So is there anything important about learning or
using modeling that we didn't cover in your opinion here, like something that you want to say,
but by chance, didn't like mention it, like something that you don't like, or you liked about
modeling. Is there anything? P1)(I think I'm going to maybe touch on the topic of frameworks.
You hear me? Yeah, I can, I can. Okay. I feel like we spoke a little bit about it, but,
you know, in my very personal opinion, I think that's something that really put me off about
modeling was the frameworks, you know, having to have a framework to me. It's weird. Of course,
there are some, you know, some principles that are good, some, you know, some standardization
that is good, but a lot of times what I feel like when I need to model is I need to show something,
you know, and using a specific framework is not always the most useful. Sometimes doing something,
you know, that you create yourself can be or can feel more, you know, intuitive and simpler,
you know, without having to use those specific, you know, drawings, you know, those specific classes. Yeah, P2)
(I understand. So you think a positive thing for like modeling would be a standardization, like
having one unique universal framework. You don't need to learn like 15 different frameworks,
UML, BPMN, ER, I started, I need to learn all those. Just one that will be useful for everything,
and it's not like that complex. P1) Yeah, that you can really abstract with, you know,
you can create your own ideas with it, you can create essentially a, I think having a lot of
different frameworks, I mean, I'm not going to, you know, how do you say it? Remember?
Remember, yeah, every tail in every single framework, I think it's too hard.
Yeah, pretty enough. Then yeah, then that's it. Thank you for your time. If, I need anything,
do you mind if I contact you later for when you go to a clarification question, something like that?
Of course, that's fine. Okay, thank you for your time, then. Have a good day.
Goodbye. Thank you.